My name is Luna Deitch. I've been doing this for 30 years.
For the first 16 years I couldn't get anybody to come out with me because nobody wanted to see this harrah.
But I come from 18 generations of rabbis, orthodox rabbis.
Nobody, nobody in my family did this. Nobody. No rabbi.
You can use a sack of money instead of swinging a chicken.
And you know, I was talking to the kids and the kids are under the misconception that this is in the Torah.
It's not. Not in the Torah. It's not in the Talmud.
It's in Shulchan Aruch, which was written in the 1500s by a Spanish rabbi by the name of Joseph K.
And he called it a foolish custom.
And unfortunately, shortly thereafter, an Ashkenazi rabbi from Eastern Europe came and he removed the negative commentary.
And he thought it was a good idea to do and he promoted things as a chicken.
That's why this is going on now.
And it's, it's not only violating 15 city and state laws, it's violating Jewish law.
The most important one is the Torah mandate not to cause harm to animals, unnecessary harm, and to help them if you can.
And there's also a Talmudic imperative in the Talmud that says feed your animals before you feed yourself.
These chickens don't get any food and water.
And as you probably have seen, there are dead ones.
They die of dehydration and starvation and heat prostration.
And when it's cold, because it goes by the Jewish calendar, sometimes it happens later in the year, it could be freezing.
They freeze to death, you know.
It was at this location once where it was raining and we captured, one of our activists captured video of them shivering and freezing to death.
It's really an awful custom.
It can be easily done with money and there's no excuse.
There's no excuse for this.
This is just blatant animal cruelty.
I've already seen two chickens with their wings broken, open fractures.
I'm a nurse by profession.
You could see the bones jutting on them and the guys holding them by the wings.
We tried to, sometimes community affairs will work with us and speak to the owner of the place and negotiate the release of the injured chickens.
But the guys covering right now, they're just doing overtime, they're not even from this precinct.
So they, you know, one of the officers went in to talk to the owner and was told that the owner's not there.
I don't believe that for a minute.
I'm sure the owner is there and it's just, it's just really awful.
It's horrible.
Horrible.
But we're trying to change that.
We used to do angry protests.
They don't work.
You know, it just makes them dig their heels in more.
This is a very insolent community.
You know, they, they are conditioned from birth to believe that this is a good thing to do.
Sometimes when the kids cry and they tug at their mother's skirts and they say,
the chicken is crying, the chicken is crying.
The mothers tell them, oh, they're not crying.
They're happy to, they're singing.
They're happy to do this.
But if I'm there, I tell them, no, you're right.
I tell the kids, I said, they are crying because it hurts them.
I tell them, like, who provided?
Thank you for documenting this.
Yeah.
I appreciate it.
And all the prophets, Jeremiah, Yeremiyahu, Hosea, they say God wants mercy, not sacrifice.
Exactly.
This goes against every, you know, compassionate tenet in the Bible, in the Torah, in the Talmud.
It's just, it's an abomination.
And it's an embarrassment to me as a Jewish person.
You know, I think this is a stain on Judaism.
You know, I come from 18 generations of Orthodox rabbis, but I am not religious myself.
However, I'm very Jewish ethnically, you know, and I try to protect my, you know, my ethnicity.
Sorry, it's okay.
I'm a nurse by profession.
I became a nurse in 1979.
I'm disabled now.
I can't work as a nurse anymore.
But, you know, I became a nurse because I can't stand to see anybody suffer without trying
to help or trying to prevent that suffering.
And it's the same reason I became a vegan 40 years ago.
Same reason I'm here with the chickens.
So, you know.
As a Jew, but also a vegan, do you feel that what's happening here is really that much different
from what's happening in a Chick-fil-A slaughterhouse?
It isn't.
It is not much different.
Except that the fact that they're really being tortured and they're being, you know, swung by their broken wings.
My cousin's a veterinarian in England and he said the wings are way too fragile to hold these big bodies.
These bodies are plumped up for their flesh.
And they're only babies.
They're five to six weeks old.
Um, no, I don't, you know, it just hurts me on every level you can imagine.
What do you, what would you say to someone who finds this appalling as you do, but also eats chickens?
Oh, that's happened many times.
When I was working in the hospital and I would show people what goes on, you know, during the ritual.
And they would be absolutely horrified while they're eating a chicken sandwich.
And I would say, you know what, the chicken you're eating suffered similarly, suffered just as much as these chickens.
And in a way, I mean, I, this is sort of important for people to see because maybe, just maybe, one makes them think about what they're eating.
You know, I know people have said to me when they've seen this, some people have said, I can't eat chicken anymore.
Well, good, that's the first step, you know, but I mean, all animals, all animals suffer.
All sentient creatures.
And I try to talk to them.
I talk to them.
I talk to people all the time, all the time.
And, you know, I mean, I'm kind of glad that this is happening out in the street so people can see it.
You know, um, they need to see what they're responsible for.
Chicken factories are behind walls.
Right.
Exactly.
And in my neighborhood of Borough Park, my orthodox neighborhood where I live, they've covered everything up since we've been out, you know, doing what we do.
And so nobody sees it here.
It's out in the open and everybody can see it.
So, I mean, I'm glad that it's in the, I'm glad that it's in the street so everybody who lives in the neighborhood and everybody driving through can see this because they need to make, start making connections to what they're eating.
They have to start making connections.